Guide to the James J. Comerford Papers AIA.010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
James J. Comerford Papers
1867-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Comerford, James J., 1901-1988
Concannon, John
AIA.010
14.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 7 oversize flat boxes.
James J. Comerford was a well-known lawyer and judge in New York City. He also served as the Chair of the St. Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee in New York City for 19 years. A recognized historian, his manuscript entitled My Kilkenny I.R.A. Days 1916-1921, along with writings on the history of Ireland are included in the papers as is correspondence between Mr. Comerford and well-known politicians and other public figures in New York and the United States. Many files pertaining to his work in the Ancient Order of Hibernians are included in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The James J. Comerford Papers were donated to the Archives of Irish America in 2004 by John Concannon. The accession number associated with this collection is 1997.051.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series. Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Missing Title
Series I. Papers and Correspondence, 1867-1985
Series II. Photographs, 1957-1970, undated
Series III. Realia, 1953-1982
Historical/Biographical Note
James J. Comerford (1901-1988), a native of Co. Kilkenny was born on New Years' Day 1901 and died at the age of 87 in 1988. In his teens Comerford joined the Irish Republican Army and discusses his experiences in the year 1920-1923 in his memoir My Kilkenny IRA Days. In 1925 he immigrated to New York City and worked at a variety of jobs including as a ticket agent for the Interborough Rapid Transit (IRT) at night while attending college during the day. When Comerford was 33 he earned a high school diploma and then at the age of 34 matriculated at Columbia to earn his Bachelor's degree. He then went on to get his Master's and JD from Fordham University. Comerford retired as a Judge of the Magistrates Court in 1971. The Judge was active in many Irish organizations and was an outspoken Irish Nationalist. He served for 19 years as chairman of the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade and was also a president of the United Irish Counties Association. Comerford was a member and National Historian of the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH) for 52 years and edited the organization's Hibernian Digest.
Comerford was married to Vera Carr. They had no children.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Irish Counties Association (AIA 003), contains a history Comerford wrote on the formation of the UICA in America (AIA 003, Box 3, Folder 18). Researchers may also be interested in the collections of the organizations of which Comerford was part, including the Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AIA 046) and the United Irish Counties Association Records (AIA 056).
Scope and Contents
The collection documents James J. Comerford's career from the 1960s onward, specifically his nomination to a Federal Judgeship, his membership in Irish American and other associations, and his personal life. Career files include correspondence from notable figures written in support of Comerford's nomination to the Federal Court. Notable correspondents include politicians such as John F. Kennedy, Robert F. Kennedy, and Tip O'Neill as well as labor union leaders such as Mike Quill of the Transport Workers Union and Harry Van Arsdale of the AFL-CIO. Of interest in the collection are Comerford's original handwritten drafts and typed manuscript for the memoir My Kilkenny IRA Days. Comerford joined the IRA in his teens and the memoir covers the years 1920-1923, providing an intimate look at the activities of this citizen soldier organization and as well as life in Ireland in the early 20th century.
Comerford kept some of his educational materials from obtaining his high school diploma, Bachelor's from Columbia University, and Master's and JD from Fordham, including course listings and grades, which can be found in Series I under Education.
Comerford was active in several organizations in New York, notably the Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee and the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH). He was also the editor of the AOH's publication, the Hibernian Digest, and the collection contains several files on his activities in the Order, as well as photographs and negatives used in the Digest. Newspaper clippings which are quite fragile and brittle with age document Comerford's career and personal life. Numerous photographs of Judge Comerford and his wife Vera are included in Series II, as are images of Comerford involved in activities pertaining to the St. Patrick's Day Parade, AOH and other associations.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Negatives (photographic); Plaques (flat objects); Correspondence.; Writings (document genre); Pamphlets.; Black-and-white photographs.; Saint Patrick's Day.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Manuscripts; Clippings (information artifacts); Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government.; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; Irish Northern Aid Committee; American-Irish Historical Society; Ancient Order of Hibernians; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Quill, Mike, 1905-1966; Concannon, John
- Series I. Papers and Correspondence, 1867-1985
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1936, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: By-Laws, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Anti-Partition Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Comerford, James J. - Speech on Partition of Ireland, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: History, 1965-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ledger, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Historians Bulletin/National Historian Bulletin, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Hibernian Digest Documentation, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Hibernian Digest Images (see Series II Photographs for photographs and negatives), 1957-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13A)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Associations: American Irish Historical Society, 1967-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Associations: American Irish Immigration Committee, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Associations: Catholic Press Association I, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Associations: Catholic Press Association II, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Associations: Democratic State Committee of New York, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Associations: Equestrian Order of the Holy Sepulcher, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Associations: Equestrian Order of the Holy Sepulcher - Certificate (oversize); two items - James Comerford and Veronica Comerford, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Associations: Irish Northern Aid Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Associations: Various, 1957-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Associations: Various, 1958-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Associations: Various, 1965-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Associations: Various-Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Career I, 1949-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Career II, 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Career III, 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Career: Biographical Information, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Career: Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Career: Publications and Articles, 1949-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Coolbawn Ambush History, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript: A Bit O' Irish History-Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript: A Bit O' Irish History-Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript: Clippings/Index, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript: "My Kilkenny I.R.A. Days 1916-1922"-Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript: "My Kilkenny I.R.A. Days 1916-1922"-Drafts I, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript: "My Kilkenny I.R.A. Days 1916-1922"-Drafts II, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal, 1971-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Personal, 1954-1974; Letter signed by Mayor John Lindsay (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Personal, 1932-1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Personal, 1958-1979; Card signed by Eamon de Valera (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Personal: Education I, 1931-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Personal: Education II, 1931-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Personal: Education III: transcripts from school in Ireland, 1908-1915 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Personal: Education IV: Class notes "Contracts", 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8A)
  - Personal: Ephemera: Certificate of Appreciation from the City of New York, signed by Mayor Lindsay, Mar 5, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Personal: Ephemera (coat of arms), 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 9A)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, 1916-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, 1951-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, 1951-1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, 1953-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Personal: Newspaper Clippings-Catholic Worker, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Personal: Pamphlets and Publications, 1935-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Personal: Pamphlets and Publications: Humorous Irish Readings. McClennon's Penny Recitors and Readings, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Personal: Pamphlets and Publications-Eire Ireland, 1966, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Personal: Writings - History of Ireland, 19th Century, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Personal: Writings "Only One Man's Little Opinion", Nov 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2A)
  - Personal: Writings "Some Unusual Facts About Past Gaelic Games in America", circa 1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee, 1960-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee, 1960-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee I, 1961-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee II, 1961-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee, 1963-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee I, 1965-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee II, 1965-1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee I, 1966-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee II, 1966-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee: Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee: Ribbons, 1961, 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee: Rules and Regulations for the Conduct of the Parade, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series II. Photographs, 1960-1970, undated
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1969-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, 1969-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians - negatives and newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1969-1970, undated (Box 6)
  - Comerford, James J. (portraits), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Comerford, James J. and Vera - Trips to Ireland, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Comerford, James J. with New York City Mayor John Lindsay (autographed by Lindsay), circa 1966-1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Comerford, James J. with Others, circa 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Comerford, James J.: Personal, unidentified (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Comerford, Vera (many with James), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Group photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Group photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Kilkenny, aerial view, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Personal, unidentified, 1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Personal, unidentified (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - St Patricks Day Parade, 1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - St Patricks Day Parade (segregated photographs), 1965 (Box 14)
  - St Patricks Day Parade (several oversize photographs; include images of Ed Koch, Roslyn Carter, Daniel Moynihan plus many aerial views from 630 5th Avenue) 7 photographs, 1965-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Speaker with Comerford, behind Harp, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Workers Union of Ireland, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series III. Memorabilia, 1953-1982
  - Book: "History of Europe: Our Own Times" by James Harvey Robinson and Charles A. Beard. Inscribed: James J. Comerford, February 1930, School Y.M.C.A. Brooklyn", 1927 (Box 6)
  - Book: "Cushing's Manual of Parliamentary Practice" 1928. Inscribed "James J Comerford" (Box 6)
  - Commendation: NYU Founders Day Award, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Daybook Calendar, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook and Daily Calendar; includes newspaper clippings, mention of Vera's death and other notes, 1980-1984 (Box 6)
  - Plaques (8): including 3 on retirement from bench, one a letter from Mayor Lindsay on retirement; contributions to Irish Culture and chairmanship of SPD Parade, 1963-1982 (Box 8, Box 10, Box 9)
  - Plate: Ancient Order of Hibernians Honorary Lifetime Membership, Aug 6, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Plaque: Ancient Order of Hibernians in America Testimonial, May 11, 1963 (Box 13)
- Series IV. Audio, 1937-1938
  - Aluminum Disk: Side 1: 1. JJC; 2. "Haynes Speech Reply" 2nd Record Part 1; Side 2: "A fox looked at his shadow" 1st Record, 2 parts, Mar 1937 - May 1937 (Box 11, Item 1)
  - Aluminum Disk: Side 1: 1. Extempo, Speaking Purpose "To Stir the Emotions"; 2. Mr. Halliday Hospital Scene onf blank side of record no makes [?sic[ name... / Recorded at Columbia University; Side 2: "Advertising" on side of makes name of record, Nov 8, 1937 (Box 11, Item 2)
  - Aluminum Disk: Side 1: Track 1. "What is your language?" ... ? ... German and French; Track 2. poem [...?...] 1938; Track 3. Burke [?] - narrow side Side 2: 1. Burke, 2. Webster, 3. Webster wide side; Webster too fast (legislation); Burke too fast (soil), Mar 2, 1938 - May 18, 1938 (Box 11, Item 3)
  - Aluminum Disk: Play with ... [?] ... Thomas Davis Players Side 1. 7. Mary O'Neill, 8. John Duffy 9. David Donaghy; Side 2. 9. David Donaghy (continuted), 10. Martin Walsh, Apr 19, 1938 (Box 11, Item 4)